בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ח. Yud-Chet.
So again, today's דף daf is י"ח. Yud-Chet. We pick up at
the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב' Yud-Zayin Amud-Bet where four lines from
the bottom. We were talking about thirteens in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. This is to get us to the thirteen שופרות, Shofaros, which
we will get to today. But first we talked about thirteen prostrations
and then thirteen שולחנות. Shulchanos. And these were the שולחנות, Shulchanos, they,
you know, they were different שולחנות, Shulchanos, those that functioned for washing
the innards, those that functioned for putting things down on them, the
שולחן Shulchan for the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. But that led to
the discussion that in the time of שלמה, Shlomo, he made ten
extra שולחנות Shulchanos to the right and the left of the שולחן
Shulchan of משה. Moshe. And now we are going to talk about
their exact placement. So we pick up four lines from the bottom.
תני, Tani, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, and this is a
סוגיא Sugya paralleled in the בבלי Bavli in מנחות. Menachos. מזרח ומערב
היו נתונים. Mizrach u'Ma'arav hayu netunim.
The שולחנות Shulchanos were aligned east-west. דברי רבי. Divrei Rebbi.
That's what רבי Rebbi says. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר
צפון ודרום היו נתונים. Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon omer Tzafon ve-Darom hayu
netunim.
They were placed.
So let's quickly sort of diagram show that.
The שולחנות Shulchanos we're talking about.
Yeah, the שולחנות. Shulchanos. So if here is your מקדש, Mikdash, whoops,
let me draw the other way so it corresponds to our actual
way of orientation. Okay.
North, south, east, west. Okay. So, you know, this is the אולם,
Ulam, this is the whole בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay. Anyway. קודש
קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Okay.
So, and here is the מזבח. Mizbei'ach.
So here's the מנורה, Menorah, right? And here's the שולחן. Shulchan. Alright.
Okay. So that's basically what it was. And the so the question
is where did they line up the extra שולחנות? Shulchanos? Did they
line them up north-south like this? And then the גמרא Gemara has
a problem if you line them up north-south, then the שולחן, Shulchan,
the real שולחן Shulchan of משה Moshe is not the northernmost. Okay.
That was the question. Or did you line them up east-west? And
that's the other opinion. So where do you line up the שולחנות?
Shulchanos? Let's take a look. Okay. So רבי שמעון אומר צפון ודרום
היו נתונים, Rabbi Shimon omer Tzafon ve-Darom hayu netunim, north-south. מאן דאמר
מזרח ומערב ניחא. Man de-amar Mizrach u'Ma'arav nicha.
If you say east-west, it's good. כולהון ראויים לשירות. Kulhun re'uyim l'sheirus.
They're all fit for service. Meaning that they're all, first of all,
accessible. Second of all, they're all northernmost. Nothing is more north than
the other. There is a debate before whether they put the bread
on all the tables or just the one of משה. Moshe. But
certainly the one of משה Moshe is also to the north. Nothing
is more north than it. So that's fine. But מאן דאמר צפון
ודרום, man de-amar Tzafon ve-Darom, but if you say it's north-south, נמצא
שולחן בדרום. nimtza Shulchan ba'darom.
So the שולחן Shulchan of משה Moshe and nine of them actually,
everyone other than the northernmost, are not the northernmost שולחן. Shulchan. So
that was the issue we raised yesterday.
Now, Lindzer, would you just briefly indicate where are the שולחנות, Shulchanos,
so to speak, of the בית המטבחיים? Beis Mitbachayim?
Oh, well those are in the עזרה. Azarah. Right here is, here's
the מזבח. Mizbei'ach. Right. Here are two שולחנות Shulchanos where they put
in order to, to bring up, you know, when they were organizing
the limbs to be brought up, and when they put the כלים.
Keilim. And up here were the שולחנות, Shulchanos, right, the בית המטבחיים,
Beis Mitbachayim, right? The slaughterhouse. Right.
Meaning because north is where you would do the קודשי קודשים Kodshei
Kodashim would be at the north of the מזבח. Mizbei'ach. So this
would be like the busiest location. So anyway, they put those there.
Okay, there'd be eight, nine, ten. They had two here, right, as
they said, for the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. Eleven, twelve. And this
was thirteen. Okay. You got that? Yeah. Good. So, alright. So if
it's north-south, the שולחן Shulchan is not in the south. המנורה בצפון
Ha-Menorah batzafon and the מנורה Menorah is in the north. Now, who's
talking about the מנורה? Menorah? Most people cross that line out. The
other thing is that it also says that שלמה Shlomo made ten
extra מנורות. Menoros. And the same question of how to align the
שולחנות Shulchanos is how to align the מנורות. Menoros. So presumably if
you align the שולחנות Shulchanos north-south, you also align the מנורות Menoros
north-south and you would have the same problem. The מנורה Menorah would
not be the southernmost. There would be מנורות Menoros that would also
be in the south or would be northern to some of the
מנורה. Menorah. Okay. Now let's try to continue to figure out which
way they were oriented. והתני, Veha tani, did we not teach? השולחן
היה נתון מחצי הבית ולפנים משוך מן הכותל שתי אמות ומחצה כלפי
צפון ומנורה כנגדו בדרום. Ha-shulchan hayah natun me-chatzi habayis u'vifnim, mashuch min
hakosel shtei amos u'mechetza klapei tzafon, u'menorah kenegdo badarom.
So
the שולחן Shulchan was halfway, basically the dimensions were this. This was
twenty אמות amos wide, forty אמות amos long until you got to
the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, plus another twenty אמות amos here. Okay.
And this says that it was halfway in. So it's not counting
the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Okay. So this is your halfway mark,
this is ten אמות amos and this is ten אמות. amos. So
the שולחן Shulchan was at... At the halfway point, starting at the
halfway point. That's where the שולחן Shulchan was. Okay. היה נתון מחציה
ולפנים, Haya natun mechatziya u'lifnim, so on the inner half, משוך מן
הכותל באמות ומחצה כלפי צפון. mashuch min hakotel be'amot u'mechtzah k'lapei tzafon.
And there was two and a half אמות amot here between it
and the wall. Why did you need a little space between it
and the wall?
The שולחן, Shulchan, to walk around it?
You have to get to the other side in order to take
out the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. The way they did the לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim is some call it on one side pushing the
old one out and pushing the new one in, and the other
was on the other side pulling the old one out. So you
had to be on both sides. Okay, so there's a little gap
here, it was from the halfway point and it was on the
inner half of it. And the מנורה Menorah was equally situated opposite
it on the south. All right, so that's how it was oriented.
Obviously, if it's only two and a half אמות amot here, there
were no other מנורות, menorot, there were no other שולחנות shulchanot between
it and the wall. Right, this obviously would have to assume it
was east-west and not north-south.
Okay. מזבח הזהב היה נתון באמצע הבית.
Mizbeach hazahav haya natun
be-emtza habayit.
So
the altar was smack in the middle of the house. חולק את
הבית מחציה ולפנים. cholek et habayit mechatziya u'lifnim.
It was divided the house halfway. So that was the halfway mark,
presumably it was not only halfway this way but it was also
halfway this way, right? It was exactly at the center. Yes, is
that clear? Meaning it was halfway from that and halfway from that.
משוך קימעא כלפי חוץ. mashuch kima k'lapei chutz.
They take out the word צפון. tzafon. A little bit drawn towards
the out. Meaning, so if this is the line and the שולחן
Shulchan and the מנורה Menorah are exactly half on the inside, this
would be halfway, but it would be pulled out, right? It was
not in between the מנורה Menorah and the
שולחן. Shulchan. So there was an open space between the מנורה Menorah
and the שולחן. Shulchan.
What was done on that מזבח? Mizbeach?
The קטורת. Ketoret. Just the burning of the קטורת. Ketoret. No, no,
no, no, no. Remember also this is all under a roof. From
the אולם Ulam in, it's all under a roof, so you cannot
be bringing animal sacrifices under a roof, okay? You could, but it
would not be good business. So this was קטורת, Ketoret, which was
done twice a day by the כהן Kohen by the כהנים, Kohanim,
once in the morning, once in the afternoon. And that would be
the only thing brought there. They would put the blood of the
inner sacrifices, like on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, they put some blood
on the corners, but basically the only thing they would do is
burn קטורת. Ketoret.
The עזרה Azarah is on the out...
The עזרה Azarah is, right, is all this stuff around it. It's
an open courtyard around it. All right.
That's the מזבח הזהב. Mizbeach hazahav.
That's the מזבח הזהב. Mizbeach hazahav. Exactly. Okay. וכולהון היו נתונים משליש
הבית ולפנים. u'chulehon hayu netunim mishlish habayit u'lifnim.
And everything was a third into the house. What do you mean
a third? You just got through saying a half. So the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi as it is once does not explain everything. But the בבלי
Bavli says no, a third is if you include the קודש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. So it was 20 אמות amot in, right? You call
it half, well it's halfway from this section, but
if you look at the entire thing including the קודש קדשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, it's 60, so it's a third.
Okay, so it's a third or a half depending on how you
count.
Okay, so now it
says... עשר מנורות. Eser menorot. Now, עשר מנורות עשה שלמה. Eser menorot
asar Shlomo. Now, by the way, so before we go on, I
want to just point out, so we have an explicit ברייתא Baraisa
that supports the idea of east-west. According to this ברייתא, Baraisa, right,
it's very clear the שולחן Shulchan was very close to the wall.
There's no way to say north-south. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi does not make
any attempt to try to reconcile it according to the opinion of
north-south or even engage it, it just has a straight ברייתא Baraisa
clearly proves east-west. So there's a very interesting comment here both by
the קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah and by the תכלין חדתין. Tachlin Chadatin.
I'll read it here in the תכלין חדתין, Tachlin Chadatin, the first
line here on י"ח עמוד א'. yud-chet amud aleph. He says, so
he says this ברייתא Baraisa obviously contradicts the north-south approach. וגם סתם
מתניתין דמנחות כוותיה דרבי ולאו אורחא דירושלמי להאריך בפלפולא שלא אליבא דהלכתא,
v'gam stam matnitin d'menachot kevata de'Rabbi v'lav orcha d'Yerushalmi l'haarich be'pilpula shelo
aliba de'hilchata, which is really a nice way of pointing out a
significant difference between the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and the בבלי. Bavli. We don't
try to make אוקימתות ukimtas and say, well, if I read it
this way, I could be מיישב meyashev it. Look, clearly the evidence
is one side, let's move on. Okay. So there is a quite
a stark difference between the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and the בבלי. Bavli.
ירושלמי Yerushalmi written by רבותינו. Rabboseinu.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. Now that we
talked about the שולחנות, Shulchanot, we're going to talk about the מנורות
Menorot and have a similar discussion. עשר מנורות עשה שלמה. Eser menorot
asar Shlomo. He made ten additional מנורות. menorot. שנאמר ויעש מנורת הזהב
עשר כמשפטם ויתן בהיכל חמש מימין וחמש משמאל. Shene'emar vayasas menorat hazahav
eser kemishpatam vayitein baheichal chamesh miyamin u'chamesh mismol. Five on the right,
five on the left. Now,
what does it mean right and left? So again, if we're talking
about the normal reference of normally we assume as I mentioned before
a person is facing east, the phrase to orient yourself, the orient
means the east, means to face yourself eastward, you face yourself towards
the rising sun. That's why one of the words for east in
the תורה Torah is קדמה, Kedma, קדם. Kedem. In front of you.
A word for south is תימנה, Temana, which is from ימין, Yamin,
your right, because if this is east, your left is north and
your right is and your right is south. So if that's what
ימין Yamin and שמאל Smol means, north south, assuming that you're oriented
to the east and right and left is north and south, we've
got the same problem we had before. אי תימא חמשה בחמש בצפון
וחמש בדרום, Im teima chamisha b’chamesh b’tzafon v’chamesh b’darom, five north and
five south, ולאו המנורה רכיא אלא בדרום? v’lo hamenora racheia ela b’darom?
Then the מנורה menora is not the southernmost, שנאמר, shena’amar, ואת המנורה
נוכח השלחן על ירך המשכן תימנה, v’et hamenora noach hashulchan al yerech
hamishkan temana, then there'll be five מנורות menorot that are more southern
than the מנורה. menorah. So מה תלמוד לומר חמשה מימין וחמשה משמאל?
ma talmud lomar chamisha mi’yamin v’chamisha mi’smol? So how do you reconcile
it? אלא חמשה מימין מנורתו של משה וחמשה משמאל, Ela chamisha mi’yamin
menorato shel Moshe v’chamisha mi’smol, five on the right and five on
the left of משה'ס Moshe’s מנורה, menorah, but they are oriented east
west, not north south. אף על פי כן, Af al pi chein,
nevertheless, לא היה מבעיר אלא בשל משה בלבד, lo haya mavir ela
b’shel Moshe bilvad,
the exact same debate by the שלחן, shulchan, exact same even discussion
what does left and right mean we're having by the מנורה. menorah.
Even though שלמה Shlomo made these extra ones, they only lit the
candles on משה'ס, Moshe’s, שנאמר, shena’amar, מנורת הזהב ונרותיה לבער בערב בערב.
menorat hazahav v’neiroteha l’va’er ba’erev ba’erev.
It uses the singular then
as the דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim continues describing as it's describing it
uses the singular and it says the מנורה menorah to kindle in
evening every evening. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר על כולן היה מבעיר.
Rabbi Yosei b’Rabbi Yehuda omer al kulana haya mavir. No, there's another
פסוק pasuk there in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim as well where it
talks about the making of the מנורה menorah and it actually there
indicates that שלמה'ס Shlomo’s placing of the מנורות menorot that they would
use all of them, שנאמר, shena’amar, ואת המנורות ונרותיהן לבערם כמשפט לפני
הדביר זהב סגור והפרח והנרות והמלקחיים זהב הוא מכלות זהב. v’et hamenorot
v’neiroteihen l’va’aram kamishpat lifnei hadvir zahav sagur v’haperech v’haneirot v’hamelkachayim zahav hu
michlot zahav.
That's the end of the פסוק. pasuk. So it says they would
kindle them before the דביר, dvir, the דביר dvir is the קודש
קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, pure gold and the flower and the lamps and
the like the tweezers, everything was מכלות זהב, michlot zahav, the purest
of gold. So basically you have a contradiction in the פסוקים pesukim
whether it indicates whether it was only משה'ס Moshe’s that was lit
or whether the other ones lit and this exactly is the debate
of אמוראים Amoraim what they really did as we had the debate
by the שלחן. shulchan. Again, it's quite shocking when you think of
the idea that שלמה Shlomo made all of these extra vessels. Again,
if you want to make some extra bowls or whatever, you want
to do something slightly different to the walls, but it would seem
so much from the תורה, Torah, you know, that the exact כלים
keilim and their placement is so precise about what the מקדש Mikdash
looks like. So number one he adds the vessels, and number two
to think that now they actually began a whole other ritual of
making more לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and lighting multiple מנורות, menorot, obviously
you understand the inclination to try to underscore the פסוק pasuk that
seems to be talking that it was only that מנורה menorah proper
of משה Moshe that in practice they used. Yes Charlie.
But why would that be surprising? The dimensions were larger, the מזבח
mizbe’ach was larger.
Yeah but you know I guess the sense is that it's one
thing to make it at a different scale, it's another thing. Yeah
I mean to me it seems.
Like בל תוסיף? bal tosif?
Yeah I mean to me it seems that it's like, you know.
To me, somehow, it seems like the exact כלים keilim were very
sort of central to you know to what the. It wasn't like
fundamentally it was a structure and you put various vessels inside. I
mean you know the whole תורה Torah sort of starts with the
vessels and works backwards right? Starts with the ארון, aron, starts with
the vessels, finally eventually you get to the structure. So it does
seem to be a little bit different to do things at a
different scale than it does to actually change those primary vessels. Anyway,
what are you going to do? שלמה Shlomo did it. But you
understand the inclination to say that they only used the one of
משה. Moshe.
מלקחיים Melkachayim are tongs, right?
Yeah what did I say, tweezers? Well that's essentially the same. Tweezers
are smaller. Tongs are bigger. Yeah but it's a different scale. There
you go. No but the מלקחיים melkachayim I think are for the
wicks I think so that's why they're more tweezer-like. I think so,
yeah. Alright anyway, so alright now we're going to do something on
the phrase מכלות זהב, michlot zahav, what that means, like the purest
of gold. הן כילו זהבו של משה. Hein kilei zehavo shel Moshe.
So the gold that they used for the מנורות, menorot, they made
an end with the gold of משה, Moshe, meaning it was like
so much more than the gold that was used in משה'ס Moshe’s
מנורה. menorah. I mean obviously they made ten but we're going to
see even more than that. Let's take a look. תני רבי יהודה
בשם אסי היה שלמה נוטל אלף ככרי זהב, Tani Rabbi Yehuda b’shem
Asi haya Shlomo notel elef kikarei zahav, he took a thousand talents
of gold, ומכניסם לכור, u’machnisam lakur, and he put them into a
furnace, ומוציאן עד שהוא מעמידם על אחד, u’motzian ad she’hu ma’amidam al
echad, and he would burn out all the impurities so he'd only
be left with one. Now I
could not really have been pure gold if you could burn out
nine hundred and ninety nine parts out of a thousand of impurities.
Actually that's the way that gold is refined today.
Yeah but not with that proportion, right?
Yeah that's about right.
What, nine hundred and ninety nine parts?
Ordinarily inefficient process today.
No no no but if you have
nine hundred and
ninety nine.
Oh, but then you wouldn't call this gold, you'd call this ore
that has gold in it, gold ore. Maybe that's what they mean.
I don't know. Anyway, but now you understand the phrase that they
ended... that they like consumed all of the gold in the making
of this. לקיים מה שנאמר ככר זהב Zahav, טהור עשה אתה *Likayem
mah shenemar kikar zahav tahor asah otah*, pure gold, and to be
pure you had to do everything to get out all the impurities.
תני ונתנא בריתא *Tani venatna beraisa*, אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *Amar
Rebbe Yossi berebbe Yehuda*, מעשה במנורת זהב שעשה משה במדבר *Maaseh bimenorat
zahav she'asah Moshe bamidbar*. The מנורה *menorah* that משה *Moshe* made והייתה
יתירה דינר dinar. זהב *vehayata yeteira dinar zahav*, and it was a
דינר dinar *dinar* extra of gold weight than it should have been.
It was a little over ככר *kikar*. Now that's fascinating. What does
that mean? משה *Moshe* got it wrong? I mean, I don't even
understand how it's describing the scenario. Maybe the second... this is what
happened when משה *Moshe* made it, that they found out when they
initially made it that it was an extra דינר Dinar. *dinar*. והכניסוה
לכור שמונים פעם *Vehikhnisuha lakur shmonim paam*. They ran it through the
furnace eighty times in order to get out the impurity ולא חסרה
כלום *veloh chasra klum*, and they couldn't... they couldn't boil it down.
They couldn't get out that extra דינר *dinar* worth. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says ויש *veyeish* that actually makes sense. עד דלא יקום
על בורייה הוי חסר Chaser סגין *Ad delo yakum al bararei havi
chasar sagi*. Before it became pure, it did not yet exist at
its purest state, so then every time you would put it in
the furnace, a lot would go away, would burn away. מן דקאיהום
על בורייה לא חסר כלום *Min dekayaum al bararei lo chasar klum*.
Once it existed at its purest state, which is the way משה
*Moshe* made it, לא חסר כלום *lo chasar klum*. You could put
it in the furnace a thousand times, there's nothing left to burn
away. It's already the purest of gold. So the furnace does not...
I mean, obviously it depends on how, I guess, hot it is,
but the furnace does not burn away gold; it only burns away
impurities. Again though, the idea that משה*'s* *Moshe's* מנורה *menorah* was a
little bit over is quite strange. Okay, so now we begin the
next one. By the way, I had forgotten yesterday, I wanted to
tell you we came up with this interesting word about a day
or two ago in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi*, דילמא *dilma*, which I
told you was a ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* word for מעשה *maaseh*. And I
knew that there was an interesting Greek etymology to it, so I
checked into it and guess what? It comes from the Greek word
drama. So the ל *lamed* and the ר *reish* sort of interchange,
but it's basically that דילמא *dilma* is drama in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*.
So it's a way and that introduces a story. All right, let's
take a look at the next משנה mishnah *mishna*. Now we get
to the reason we're talking about all these thirteens, or the reason
it's in our מסכת *masechet*, and that is for the issue of
the שופרות shofaros. *shofarot* where they would put money. And this might
not... some of this is about שקלים shekalim *shekalim*, but as you've
seen before, we talked about sanctifying things and other types of issues
that it's all a lot of issues around money given to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, not limited to שקלים *shekalim*. שלושה
עשר שופרות shofaros היו במקדש *Shlosha asar shofarot hayu bamikdash*. There were
thirteen שופרות shofaros *shofarot*. Again, these שופרות *shofarot* are sort of pyramidal...
a pyramidal צדקה
*tzedakah* boxes. And therefore you put a thing in and then you
can't, you know, sticking your hand and get anything out. It only
has a very narrow opening at the beginning... at the top. So
kept people honest. There were thirteen of them. וכתוב עליהן *Vekatuv aleihen*.
Here's what was written on them. תקלין חדתין taklin chadatin, *Taklin chadatin*.
One was written new שקל shekel, *shekel*, for this year's שקל shekel,
*shekel*. תקלין עתיקין *Taklin atikin*. Old שקל shekel *shekel*, for if you
had to pay up last year's and you... you were late. קינים
*Kinnim*. One says קינים *kinnim*, which is like birds. וגוזלי עולה olah,
*Vegozeley olah*. גוזל *Gozal* was also a bird, but like chicks. עולה
olah, *Olah* chicks. So there was two things for birds. We'll talk
about what that was used for. עצים etzim *Atzim*, עצים etzim *etzim*.
One for wood, if you wanted to make a donation in order
to for to put wood on the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. לבונה levonah,
*Levonah*.
The incense. Now this is actually quite fascinating that you are allowed
to... the תורה Torah. *Torah* never says this. The תורה Torah *Torah*
only says that if you wanted to give a freewill sacrifice, right,
you could give a שלמים shlamim, *shelamim* or you could give an
עולה olah *olah*. And what can an עולה olah. *olah* be made
out of? According to ויקרא *Vayikra*, made out of... what can it
come from? According to the beginning of ויקרא *Vayikra*, cattle, sheep. Now
and the immediate פרשה *parsha* afterwards is מנחה mincha. *mincha*, cause in
a way that's a type of an עולה olah *olah*, although it's
not all consumed. But anyway, out of flour. Well, come along חזל
Chazal *Chazal* and they actually say there's two other types of sacrifices
you could give as a freewill sacrifice that's not even mentioned in
the תורה Torah *Torah*. One is the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim *minchat
nesachim*. You could give the type of the מנחה Mincha *mincha* that
would come with the קרבן korban. *korban*, which would be a certain
amount of wine and a certain amount of oil mixed with flour,
different amounts for sheep and for cattle and so on, we discussed
that before. You could donate one of those units, not any arbitrary
amount, but one of those units to just be offered up straight
away, not without the... without any animal קרבן korban. *korban*. And the
other thing they say that you could bring is קטורת ketores *ketoret*.
Now not you... you could offer, the קטורת ketores, *ketoret* would be
brought. I gotta tell you, if I had an option of what
to bring, I mean קטורת Ketores. *ketoret* seems lovely. You bring it
in the inside of the... you know, of the... of the היכל
*Heichal*. It's frankincense. So it's interesting that that would not be an
option that a lot of people would go for, but interestingly
again, not in the תורה Torah. *Torah*, but according to חזל Chazal
*Chazal*, this is an option for donating a קרבן korban? *korban*... or
for bringing, I should say, a קרבן korban *korban*, for bringing a
freewill קרבן Korban *korban*. and here it was money that you could
donate. I'll read it to you from the רמב"ם. Rambam. He says
like this. This is in הלכות מעשה קרבנות. Hilchos Ma'aseh Korbanos. Says:
מתנדב אדם ונודר
עולה ושלמים, mitnadev adam venoder olah ushlamim, וכל מין שירצה מחמישה מיני
מנחות, vechol min sheyirtzeh mechamishah minei menachos, so that's in the תורה.
Torah עולה, olah שלמים, Shelamim? and a מנחה. Okay, ומתנדב ונודר מנחה
ממנחת נסכים לבדה, umitnadev venoder mincha miminchas nesachim levadah, or you can
just do the מנחת נסכים which normally in the תורה Torah only
comes with a קרבן. korban מאיזה מין משלושה מיני מנחת נסכים, me'eizeh
min mishloshah minei minchas nesachim, when any one of the three there
mentioned in the תורה Torah that comes either with the איל ayil
or with the כבש keves or with the פר. par. ומתנדב ונודר
יין בפני עצמו, umitnadev venoder yayin bifnei atzmo, or even wine by
itself. או לבונה בפני עצמה. o levonah bifnei atzmah. או שמן בפני
עצמו. o shemen bifnei atzmo. Or you could do you could do
just wine, just oil. או עצים למערכה, o etzim lama'aracha, and the
עצים etzim we have. Now that's not a big חידוש, chiddush, I
mean okay, they needed firewood, but the חידוש chiddush is that the
עצים etzim, are treated almost as a type of a
קרבן. korban. מפני שהוא כקרבן, mipnei shehu kekorban, שנאמר ולקורבן העצים. shene'emar
ulekorban ha'etzim. And the בבלי Bavli even has a question whether when
you would bring עצים etzim that were donated as a נדר, neder,
right, not that they used for communal funds to buy the to
buy the firewood, but somebody donated it as a private נדר, neder,
would you put salt on it? Because it says על כל קרבנך
תקריב מלח. al kol korbanecha takriv melach. How much would the wood
actually be treated as a type of a קרבן? korban? So it
is quite fascinating that חז"ל understand that there's an expanded range of
opportunities to bring free-will sacrifices not mentioned in the תורה. And that's
what this קטורת Ketores is. Okay, so you had עצים, eitzim, קטורת,
Ketoret so what are we up to? Four. No, we
had we had the two שקל, shekel the two birds, עצים eitzim
and לבונה, Levonah, that's six. זהב לכפורת, zahav lakaporeth, you could donate
money that would go for the כפורת. kaporet. Now we had this
phrase before which is quite bizarre. The כפורת kaporet was the cover
of the ארון. Aron. How much gold would you it was already
made. How would you need any more gold? So the מפרשים mefarshim
try to say that this is generic and it really means for
like the for the like the כלי שרת, klei shares, the כלי
שרת. klei shares. Although it is funny that it calls it לכפורת.
lakaporeth. Okay, so that gets
you to seven, ושישה לנדבה, veshishah lenedavah, and six for free will
which is going to mean עולות, olos, והמה עולות veheima olos as
we talked about before, right that's called קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbeach. When
the מזבח mizbeach wasn't nobody was bringing any קרבנות, korbanos, you draw
on these funds to bring these free-will עולות, olos, the money that
was donated or other funds in order that the מזבח Mizbeach. would
always be busy. Now, now we're going to go back and discuss
each one of these. תקלין חדתין, new שקל, shekel. שבכל שנה ושנה,
shebechol shanah veshanah, to each year's שקל shekel. you would you when
you came to give your שקל shekel, you put it in that.
And then remember what would they do? They would empty that out,
put it in the לשכה, lishkah, in the room, and then they
would three times a year remove the שקלים from the לשכה lishkah
and that would be the תרומת הלשכה. terumas halishkah. And that would
be they would start applying it to the קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so
that would be for the שופרות. ועתיקין, va'atikin, old
ones, מי שלא הביא אשתקד שוקל לשנה הבאה. mi shelo heivi eshtakad
shokel lishanah haba'ah. If you didn't bring last year, there would be
what is it like tax amnesty, you could come ahead and give
it this year. And that would be when you're paying up last
year's שקל. shekel? I don't know if you could go back two
or three years, but anyway it would be last year's שקל. קנים,
kinim, bird sacrifices, הן תורין. hein torin. Those are the older birds,
the pigeons. וגוזלי עולה הן בני יונה. vegozlei olah hein benei yonah.
Those are the turtledoves, the two types of bird עולות olos that
the תורה allows for. Okay, כולם עולה, kulam olah, and those would
be עולה, olah. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehudah. Basically it's another
type of a free-will sacrifice. Maybe you want to give big birds,
maybe you want to give small birds. Okay, but these are the
עולות olos which are the you know these this is one form
of an עולה olah, is to give it as birds. That's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah said. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, no. קנים אחד
חטאת ואחד עולה. kinim echad chatas ve'echad olah. גוזלי עולה כולם עולה.
gozlei olah kulam olah. No, the difference of having two different שופרות
is if you put it in the word קנים kinim because קנים
kinim by the way does not mean older birds, קנים kinim is
just a generic, it comes from the word קן ken or קן
kan which means a a nest. So קנים kinim actually would be
when very often in certain purification processes you would have to bring
two birds, one for חטאת, chatas, one for an עולה. olah, It
happens a lot with a woman who's a זבה zavah or a
יולדת, yoledes, and therefore he says that what you would do is
you would just put the money in there and קנים kinim would
then be understood that any money that goes in would be split
half for an עולה olah half for חטאת, chatas, and then if
you had to do this for your purification process, rather than having
to go buy the birds and bring it to the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, you put your money in the שופר, shofar, you'd go
home, and they would make sure that they would use up that
money each day and bring the appropriate number of sacrifices, and they
would do it for whoever gave the money, you know you don't
you could have blanket intention. And therefore that is how you would
bring your obligatory sacrifices, not just free-will is just by putting the
money in. So that's quite interesting that as opposed to animal קרבנות,
korbanos, which you know animals they're all animals whatever, cows and sheeps
and goats that you'd actually bring and give the animal, here you
would just throw the money in and you'd know that they take
care of it by the end of the day, split the money
one for חטאת chatas This one for you you have to assume
that there was a fixed price for birds, right? Or else how
many people, you don't know how many people have donated the money.
But if there was a fixed price, then you just divide it
into two and you're safe. Okay. Now somebody says הרי עלי עצים,
Harei alai etzim, I obligate myself to bring wood to the בית
המקדש, לא יפחות משני גזירין. Lo yifchos mishnei gezirin. He can't give
less than two, you know, two logs and here we're talking about
putting money in, so you have to give the value of two
logs, enough money to buy two logs. לבונה, Levonah if somebody says
I accept upon myself to give frankincense, לא יפחות מקומץ. Lo yifchos
mikometz. He can't give less than a handbreadth, that's the assumed minimum
and therefore that's the amount of money you have to put in
that שופר. shofar. זהב, I'll give gold, לא יפחות מדינר זהב. Lo
yifchos midinar zahav. He can't give less than one gold
דינר. Yeah, it was certainly I don't know, Charlie might know better,
I mean a דינר in Roman times was a lot of money.
What would it be roughly? A hundred dollars like, something like that?
Precious metals were much more rare back then so that was a
lot of money back then.
Would you say more or less than a hundred dollars roughly speaking?
I would say it'd be more. More?
Okay. Modern equivalent but the Romans also debased currency so
it depends exactly where.
Okay. All right. So השישה לנדבה, Hashishah linedavah, now what was the
generic נדבה nedavah for? נדבה מה היו עושים בה, Nedavah mah hayu
osim bah, what would they do with all that money?
לוקחים בה עולות, Lokchim bah olos, they would take an עולה olah.
meaning again a like an animal, you know, an animal, whatever, a
cow, a sheep and they'd bring it as an עולה. olah. This
would be called the קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach for when like nothing
was being brought. הבשר לשם, Habasar l'Shem, the meat would be for
God, that's what you do by an עולה, olah the meat gets
burnt on the altar. והעורות לכהנים, Vehaoros l'kohanim, at least the כהנים
kohanim would benefit from the leather. Now the
reason it's pointing that out, that's always true by an עולה, olah
is because it ties into this פסוק pasuk where they base it
on. זה מדרש שדרש יהוידע כהן גדול, Zeh midrash shedarash Yehoyada kohein
gadol, this is a מדרש midrash that יהוידע כהן גדול Yehoyada kohein
gadol interpreted, which is quite fascinating, having a כהן גדול kohein gadol
interpreting the
פסוקים. pesukim. אשם הוא אשם אשם לה'. Asham hu asham asham l'Hashem.
It is an אשם, asham, he has
totally sinned to God. So what does that mean? An אשם asham
normally means like a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham the owners
eat and then it says אשם אשם לה'. asham asham l'Hashem. So
זה הכלל, Zeh haklal, this is the rule, כל שבא משום חטאת
ומשום אשמה, Kol sheba mishum chatas umishum ashamah, if one of the
moneys that would go for the קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbeach you might
remember is if you had an אשם asham that let's say couldn't
be used, the owner's died, you'd wait till it got a מום,
mum, you'd you know you transfer the value and the money would
go for an עולה olah. for קיץ המזבח, kayitz hamizbeach, or if
you had מעות חטאת. ma'os chatas. Normally it would be let die
if it couldn't be used, the animal itself. But let's say you
had מותר חטאת. mosar chatas. You set aside a hundred dollars for
a חטאת chatas and you sanctified it and you only needed to
use eighty. What do you do with the leftover twenty dollars? So
the הלכה halacha is מותר חטאת mosar chatas goes for קיץ המזבח,
kayitz hamizbeach, goes for exactly this purpose, gets used in bringing the
עולה. olah Now that's a bizarre idea, the קדושה kedusha of a
חטאת chatas or an אשם asham gets transformed and is brought as
an עולה. olah So where do you learn it from? So he
learns it from this פסוק pasuk that's talking about an אשם. asham.
כל שבא משום חטאת ומשום אשמה, Kol sheba mishum chatas umishum ashamah,
anything that's coming for a sin or for a חטאת chatas or
an אשם, asham, ילקח בהן עולות, yilakach bahen olos, you bring an
עולה olah. with that money. הבשר לשם והעורות לכהנים, Habasar l'Shem vehaoros
l'kohanim,
so the meat goes to God and the skin goes to the
כהנים, kohanim, so that fulfills the פסוק. pasuk. It's אשם אשם לה',
asham asham l'Hashem, it gets it's all
to God, but אשם הוא, asham hu, it's like a normal חטאת
chatas or an אשם asham that the כהנים kohanim get some benefit
out of it, they get the skin. נמצאו שני כתובים קיימים, Nimtze'u
shenei kesuvim kayamim, אשם לה' ואשם לכהן. Asham l'Hashem v'asham l'kohein. ואומר,
Veomer, and another פסוק pasuk which emphasized... now in that פסוק pasuk
אשם הוא אשם אשם לה', asham hu asham asham l'Hashem, you don't
see so much the כהן kohein aspect, right? I tried to read
it into the word אשם הוא asham hu like a normal חטאת.
chatas. But in the next פסוק pasuk you see the כהן kohein
aspect. The פסוק pasuk not in תורה but in מלכים. Melachim. כסף
אשם וכסף חטאות לא יובא בית ה' לכהנים יהיו. Kesef asham v'kesef
chatas lo yuva beis Hashem lakohanim yihyu. So here you see the
כסף kesef of an אשם asham and a חטאת chatas goes to
the כהנים, kohanim, but the other פסוק pasuk says it goes to
ה'. Hashem. So we bring an עולה Olah, and everybody gets a
part of it. So this is the idea that extra money of
a חטאת chatas and extra money of an אשם asham or a
transferred אשם asham goes as an עולה. Olah, I'll remind you by
the way about this
thing about כהנים kohanim דורשים פסוקים dorshim pesukim that you might remember
way back in the first פרק perek where it spoke about the
question about does a כהן kohein have to give a שקל, right?
Everybody remember that question, does a כהן kohein have to give a
שקל? And it says שהכהנים דורשים מקרא זה לעצמם shehakohanim dorshim mikra
zeh l'atzmam on I'm trying to remember where... yeah, I'm trying to
remember where that was, it's hard to forget that. Maybe it wasn't
the first פרק... perek... maybe it was, hold on, let me just
see if I can find it. Yeah, it was on ג עמוד
ב. Gimel amud bais. אמר לו רבי יוחנן בן זכאי לא כי
אלא כהן שאינו שוקל חוטא אלא שהכהנים דורשים מקרא זה לעצמם וכל
מנחת כהן כליל תהיה. Amar lo Rabi Yochanan ben Zakai lo ki
ella kohein she'eino shokel chotei ella shehakohanim dorshim mikra zeh l'atzmam vechol
minchas kohein kalil tihyeh. So it was very interesting in two times
in one פרק perek you have the כהנים kohanim ד... Okay, let's
take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara תניא ותנא ברייתא Tanya
v'itana braisa אמר רבי יהודה לא היה שופר שקלים בירושלים. amar Rabbi
Yehuda lo haya shofar shekalim b'Yerushalayim. Now remember רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says the שופר shofar all went to עולות. olos. He did not,
obviously if you have to bring a חטאת chatas bird you bring
it, but we did not have the money go in there and
that we would just bring it for you. The money in those
two שופרות for birds would all be עולות, olos, not your obligatory
חטאת. chatas. לא היה שופר שקלים בירושלים מפני התערובת.
Lo haya shofar shekalim b'Yerushalayim
mipnei hata'aroves.
And now we find out why he in principle rejects this. Again,
it's quite fascinating, right,
because this goes to the whole question about what were the actual
facts, right? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda lived a good, whatever it was,
hundred years after חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, but he feels that in
principle they couldn't have allowed it. So he's rejecting the idea that
this actually happened because for him it would not have been acceptable
in principle. Why would it not have been acceptable in principle for
there to be a שופר shofar for that money would be used
for a חטאת? chatas? What would happen if somebody put in money
for the חטאת, chatas, went home, and died? Okay, before they got
to use that money. So now money of a חטאת מתה chatas
meisa is mixed up. Now in the same way a חטאת מתה
chatas meisa you can't bring, money that's mixed up you can't bring,
and you can't therefore bring anything because you don't know which of
the money is from the חטאת מתה. chatas meisa. So you wouldn't
be able to use any of your money. So he says, no,
no, no, we're not going to allow. If an עולה Olah. the
owner dies, fine, you can bring an עולה Olah after a person
is dead. So if it's we're talking about a חטאת, chatas, we're
going to need the person to bring it him or herself and
wait around till we're מקריב makriv it. We're not going to let
them throw the money in and not know what happened to them.
Okay, so therefore in principle I cannot expect that they used that
money for that for a חטאת. chatas. None of the principles of
ביטול bitul and רוב. rov. Right. So generally by ביטול bitul and
רוב, rov, now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda generally says מין במין לא
בטיל, min b'min lo batil, but even the rabbis that disagree with
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say עולין לא מבטלין זה את זה. olin
lo mevatlin zeh es zeh. So yes, there are סוגיות sugyos in
about whether ביטול bitul and רוב rov can apply in this realm.
He's obviously assuming not. That could be an answer. Another answer could
be, you know, we're לא חייש lo chaysh for those eventualities. You
know, everybody has a חזקה chazakah of being alive. We don't, is
it possible? Everything's possible. But we're not going to be חייש chaysh
for it. Okay, but he says in principle I can't accept this.
שמא תמות אחת מהן, Shema tamus achas meihen, one of the owners,
not one of the birds. ונמצאו דמי חטאות מתות מעורבות בהן, v'nimtzu
dmei chatayos meisos me'uravos bahen, and the money of a
חטאת, chatas, not that
the חטאת chatas is dead but that the owner is dead, is
mixed up in all the rest of the money. So the גמרא
Gemara says, והתניא, v'hatanya, is it really true that he could say
that they didn't do it? Didn't we teach in a ברייתא? braisa?
האישה שאמרה הרי עלי קן. Ha'ishah she'amrah harei alai kan. Now the,
everybody switches the גירסא girsa because we are talking about a חטאת.
chatas. Anybody says הרי עלי, harei alai, it's free will and it's
a עולה. Olah It is not a חטאת. chatas. Okay. So therefore
they switch the גירסא girsa to rather than saying האישה שאמרה ha'ishah
she'amrah to say האישה שיש עליה לידה או זיבה. ha'ishah she'yesh aleha
leidah o zivah. Okay, they say that a woman who has an
obligation to bring bird sacrifices, either she just gave birth or she
was a זבה. zavah. Okay, so she has an obligation to bring
a sacrifice. מביאה דמי קן, mavia dmei kan, or she brings קן
ken actually it should be. She brings the money for two birds.
ונותנה בשופר, v'nosnah b'shofar, and she puts it in the שופר. shofar.
ואוכלת בקדשים, v'ocheles b'kodashim, and she goes home and she, not that
night, not that day, but that night after the קרבנות korbanos she
can assume that the money was used that day. Okay, why? ואינה
חוששת שמא נתעצלו בהן. v'einah chosheshas shema nis'atzlu bahen. She doesn't have
to be concerned maybe they were lazy and didn't use the money
that was in that שופר. shofar. ואין כהן חושש. v'ein kohen choshesh.
Okay, so, so ואין כהן חושש שמא דמי חטאת מתה מעורבת בהן.
v'ein kohen choshesh shema dmei chatas meisa me'ureves bahen. And the ברייתא
braisa goes on to say, or that the כהן kohen does not
have to be concerned, now that, that, that she died. She doesn't
have to be concerned the כהן kohen didn't use the money; they
would use up the money each day. And the כהן kohen does
not have to be concerned that the people who put the money
in died. So you see it's against רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now
I don't know why it's such a question, מני? manei? רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is a תנא. tanna. Fine, it's against him. The very
fact that it has her putting money of a חטאת chatas in
a שופר, shofar, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda denied that they put the
money of a חטאת chatas in a שופר. shofar. So this is
going according to the approach that says they did use it for
that. But this is now brought as not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. Number one, they put the money in the שופר, shofar, and
number two, it says, which is consistent with except putting the money
in the שופר, shofar, that you didn't have to be concerned that
the owner would die. Yes. Wasn't it the חטאי עלי chatei Eli
what, they would take, the women would come with the קרבן Korban,
and they would delay. Right. Right, right, right. But that's not what
we're afraid of here. And that's also because the women would hang
around so that they would use this as, you know, the, you
know, they would use it for, you know, for immoral purposes, in
order to, in order to, in order to compromise the women. To
extort and compromise the women. Here you put the money in and
you'd leave. Sacrifice. Right, here you put the money in and you'd
leave. I do wonder why of all things do we say that,
you know, you, all other animal sacrifices you bring and here you
just throw the money in and you leave? I don't know why
by the birds. I can, there could be two interesting reasons suggest
themselves. One is that birds were allowed, you know, cheaper and it's,
and also they'll like make a mess over you if you try
to carry them and it's a messy business I think with the
birds more than the animals. And it's just easier to just take
your money and the animals maybe, you know, people Had their flock
and they would naturally bring one of their flock, it was more
their personal, often not just something they bought. Another interesting thing is
that a lot of the bird sacrifices are brought by women, so
you wonder is there an idea here that they're trying to get
women to get out of the way quicker? Just give them money
and leave and we'll take care of it. I don't know, but
it's interesting why of all things. Okay, so anyway, here you see
it says that they would put some money in. So now there's
a question if this line that the כהן Cohen didn't have to
be concerned is the line from the ברייתא Braisa or is it
the גמרא Gemara pointing it out? But either way, that's clear that
you could just put the money of a חטאת Chatas in and
you didn't have to worry, not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
the גמרא Gemara says, yes? Why do we assume these נדבות nidvohs
are עולות, Olos, not שלמים? Shelamim, Because a סתם נדבה, stam nidvah,
I mean you could bring a שלמים, Shelamim but if you just
have these generic, so in a way the תורה starts with עולה,
the first, the basic way of giving something is giving it fully.
But a שלמים is a more interesting type of a category, you
partake in it yourself and so on. But yes, but this idea
of just I'm just going to make a donation is like you
give something over fully and that in a קרבן would translate as
an עולה, which is interesting because there's a הלכה halacha that if
somebody says הרי עלי קרבן, Harei Alai Korban, guess what you bring
if you just say הרי עלי קרבן. Harei Alai Korban. Any guesses?
You bring a what? You would think an עולה. You know what
you bring? You bring קטורת. Because, I'm just trying to find it
in the רמבם. Hold on, because because let me just see if
I can find it, but because קטורת is the one thing that
goes fully להשם L'Hashem of anything that is burnt on a מזבח.
mizbeiach Because even, it's all ריח ניחוח, Reyach Nichoach, even the עולה
is, what do you call it? Even the עולה the כהנים Kohanim
get the skin. So it's quite fascinating. But anyway, the idea is
that it goes fully to God. Right. Okay, and they can't burn
the bones, good point. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, כי קאמרינן
ki kamrinan or כי קאמרה, ki kamra, when did רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda say I'm afraid that the money is mixed up? בחטאת שמתו
בעליהן ודאי. Bechatas shemesu ba'aleyhen vada'i. If we know the owner died,
then it's going to really be a problem. Okay, now the question
is what the heck do you mean? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda didn't
just say his הלכה halacha if the owners died. רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda denying that they had a שופר Shofar for this purpose because
he was concerned about the eventuality that somebody would die. So it's
not at all clear to me how they're trying to be משיב
meyashiv רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda with this ברייתא. Braisa. The simpler sense
is this ברייתא Braisa is the anti-רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position. It
says we do accept the money for a חטאת Chatas and we're
not concerned that the owners will die. Okay, but anyway, Joe, Joe,
pull up your foot, you're pulling the wire. Okay. So, okay, but
anyway some try to see that somehow it's saying that even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not concerned it will happen, he's only concerned
when it happens. But if that's true, I don't understand why רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't allow for there to be a שופר Shofar
for a חטאת. Chatas. Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara says another point:
ואי אמרינן נברר ארבע זוזי ונשדי בנהרא. V'ee amrinan nivrar arba zuzei
v'nishdi b'nahara. Wait, wait, I got a solution! It's sort of like
those who said why don't we use ביטול? bittul? Well, why don't
we use something else that we sometimes use, particularly we often use
this by עבודה זרה avodah zarah that gets mixed up. Take four
זוז, zuz, which is just a way of saying whatever the appropriate
sum of money is, and throw it in the ocean and say
that that money was the money that got mixed that was from
that owner that died. Okay, if we find out that an owner
actually died. We're not going to do it every time, but if
we find out an owner died, what about this as a solution?
So the גמרא says that you can't do. ואידך לישתרו V'idach lishtryan
and the rest of the money be permissible? והאמרינן בעלמא רבי יהודה
לית ליה ברירה. Veha'amrinan b'alma Rabbi Yehuda leisa leh breirah. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda doesn't hold of ברירה. breirah. Now I have to tell
you that this is a very strange use of the phrase of
ברירה breirah because ברירה breirah normally at least in the בבלי Bavli
means when you stipulate at the beginning and you let the future
events define what you meant. So you'll say I am now taking
תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros from this pile of fruit. The fruit that
I am taking is the piece of fruit that will be left
over by tomorrow. Okay, so I'm making it clear now I'm doing
the act, but what the content of that act is will be
defined based on future events. That's ברירה. breirah. This is not ברירה,
breirah, this is magic. This is basically saying I'm going to take
four זוז zuz and assume that it's the four זוז zuz that
I want. Okay, that's not ברירה, breirah, that's what the בבלי Bavli
sometimes called אמרינן, amrinan, we'll say, we'll conveniently say that these are
the four, this is the money from the person who donated it
who died. Anyway, the time we find that you can throw something
away and pretend is when anyway ביטול bittul already worked. ביטול bittul
already worked, somehow it doesn't look right, and therefore sometimes חזל will
say take something and throw it out once it already was effective
based on ביטול. bittul. Okay, but just to say this automatically helps
me find the one I was looking for. Somebody told me about
he had a friend once who wanted an umbrella, didn't have an
umbrella. So he went over to the lost and found at the
MTA, at the subway and said I lost an umbrella. So the
guy had like a thousand umbrellas, he took one and he said
is this. Now maybe again the ירושלמי means as Dos said, ביטול
bitul should work, and if ביטול bitul but we don't like the
idea that there's money mixed up, so we do this combined with
ביטול bitul as a way of as making it appear like we
got rid of the money. If it's already based on ביטול, bitul,
that's more understandable, but it's quite fascinating that it used this phrase
ברירה. breira. The bottom line is רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda does not
have a solution for this, and because he does not have a
solution for this, he does not allow חטאת Chatas money to be
placed in the שופר. shofar. If you want to bring a חטאת,
Chatas, you gotta bring it by yourself. Yes.
Why couldn't you take the coins and say wherever the coins of
that חטאת Chatas were that died?
Oh, good question, because you can't transfer the קדושה kedusha of a
of חטאת המתה. Chatas hamaisa. Now, why you can't do it by
coins because money normally you can transfer קדושה kedusha and so on.
Right, exactly my point. Yeah, that's a good question. Do we give
that why we give that status to the money?
I'll have to get back to you on that. That's a good
question. Because normally by money there isn't an issue of transferring the
קדושה. kedusha. Okay, so let's take a look now as the גמרא
continues. רבי יוסי ברבי בון אמר רבי אבא בר ממל בעא. Rabbi
Yossi Berabbi Bun Amar Rabbi Abba Bar Memel Ba'ei. So he asks
the following question. אמר הרי עלי עץ. Amar harei alai eitz. If
somebody said not I will bring עצים, but they said I will
bring an עץ. eitz. So מהי גזר אחד? Mei'i gezer echad? So
can you bring one, you know, one log? If you say עצים
means two logs, if you said עץ, eitz, could that mean one
log? Or do we say no, there's no קרבן of wood that's
less than one log that's less than two logs? So אמר רב
אלעזר מתניתא אמרה כן. Amar Rav Elazar masnisa amrah kein. Now our
our ברייתא braisa shows us why. שזה קרבן בפני עצמו וזה קרבן
בפני עצמו. Shezeh korban bifnei atzmo vezeh korban bifnei atzmo. Our משנה
shows it that each log is considered has a status of being
a קרבן. How do you know one log has a status of
being a קרבן? כהיא דתנינן תמן ביומא. Kehai desanan taman b'Yoma. שנים
בידם שני גזרי עצים. Shnayim beyadam shnei gizrei eitzim. That when they
would bring the wood on the מזבח mizbeiach. in the morning, they
would always put new wood on the מזבח. mizbeiach If you remember
anybody learned those משניות mishnayos in יומא Yoma where it talked about
how you got thirteen כהנים kohanim to do all the different pieces
of the process of bring the תמיד tamid and you know the
morning sacrifice, well two of the כהנים kohanim would be given the
job of bringing the wood. Each כהן kohen would bring one log
of wood. So if one כהן kohen is putting one log of
wood up, you see that it has the status of some in-
some independently significant type of a, you know, of a minimum offering.
And therefore it is possible to give even just one log of
wood. רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi omer עובין
אמה באמה באמה שוחקת. Uvyan amah b'amah b'amah sochakes. Their thickness of
the of the log is an אמה, amah, which is big like
a foot and a half thick, so you know, really you're talking
about a really thick log. באמה שוחקת. B'amah sochakes. And that's a
loose אמה, amah, like you know an אמה amah measured loosely, which
means more than exactly an אמה. amah. באמה שוחקת. B'amah sochakes. ארכן
Arkan but their length is באמה גדומה. b'amah gedumah. That they're an
אמה amah long but they're actually a a miniature, a midget אמה.
amah. So it's not really a full אמה amah long, which is
funny that you call the width which is the which is the
longer one the width but okay the length, but it's you know
also it grows like a tree so width is defined by the
way it grew. The width is a little more than an אמה
amah and the length is less than an אמה. amah. Why is
that? So רב חוני בשם רב אמי Rav Chuni besheim Rav Ami
כמין טורטני. kemin turtani. He says like a טורטני. turtani. Now if
you remember, so so טורטני turtani is explained to be a type
of the arm used in a balance. So he presumably is saying
that it's not so thick, it's thinner actually because it's pretty bizarre,
you see the picture. Yeah, so it's pretty bizarre. I mean, you
know, these these the, you know, and it's pretty bizarre to be
thinking about bringing a log that basically is like a square. Anyway,
but now we're going to see why it's important to be less
than an אמה. amah. אמר רבי שמואל ברבי יצחק Amar Rabbi Shmuel
Berabbi Yitzchak מפני שלא היה מקום המערכה אלא אמה. Mipnei shelo hayah
makom hama'arachah ela amah. But the actual place where they would have
the fire would only be an אמה. amah. Now that's pretty shocking,
like, because you normally assume you need a huge fire for all
of the קרבנות. korbanos. But that would only be an אמה amah
על אמה. al amah. And therefore the wood can't be protruding outside
of the actual square which is don't you know which is where
the fire where the wood is burned. So therefore it has to
be a little shorter than an אמה. amah. ולפיכך Ulefikach it was
shorter than an אמה. amah. לא היה בו אלא אמה גדומה. Lo
hayah bo ela amah gedumah. And that's why it was a short
אמה. amah. דתני כן Desani kein and we taught similarly. אמה היסוד
ואמה סובב ואמה כרכוב ואמה קרנות ואמה מערכה. Amah hayesod v'amah soveiv
v'amah karkov v'amah kranos v'amah ma'arachah. So basically the יסוד yesod and
the סובב soveiv we don't have to worry about, that's sort of
a different way in which, right? So the מזבח was sort of
as this is like a side view, you know, first there was
the יסוד yesod and then there was like then it went in
like this and then it went like that, right? This is like
a side view and then the same thing down there okay. So
that's so anyway so this goes in an אמה amah this goes
in an אמה, amah, you know, as you're going up, you know,
that's the יסוד yesod and the סובב soveiv but here is where
we care because if you have an אמה amah for the קרנות.
kranos. And an אמה *amah* for the like a כרכוב *karkov*, which
is an extra אמה *amah* inside here, right? So if you think
about how that shrinks it, if you have one אמה *amah* given
to the קרנות *kerenot* and one אמה *amah* like some type of
a walkway, right? So there's two אמות *amot* inset each side, right?
You see that, two אמות *amot* inset on each side. So if
the center is one by one, and now we just said that
there's a two extra on each side, the whole thing is five
by five. So the whole, is that clear, right? You know, you
add, right, two here and two here, that's five and five. So
the whole surface of the מזבח *mizbeach* is 25 אמות *amot* by
25. Of the top is 25 by 25. But once you keep
on going in, now it's not exactly a square, a five by
five. But it's really, it's really bigger than that because they had
more on the מזבח *mizbeach* than just the, than just the woodpile.
They had five different fires going on the מזבח *mizbeach*. It was
a very large surface, it was not only this square. So it
is strange why they're trying to quote all of this stuff because
it's not, you know, what I just showed is not really what
it is, it's really much bigger than that, the surface area. I
mean, they're sitting enough to cook a single cow. Right. So actually,
and if you look at other places, it's very clear, right, that
the מזבח *mizbeach* was bigger. I mean, it started here basically like
32 by 32. So even after you've gone in an אמה *amah*
here and an אמה *amah*. Anyway, it's going to be much, much
bigger than that. So really, what, what is it trying to prove
by the קרנות *kerenot*? Maybe it's not trying to prove that that
was what you're left with as surface area, maybe it's just quoting
that, you know, different things that are an אמה *amah*. And one
of the things that is an אמה *amah* is the מערכה *ma'arachah*.
But again, I don't get it. Even if you have a lot
of surface space on the top, which you did, and you have
the woodpile is an אמה *amah* by an אמה *amah*, how much
can you burn there given the קרבנות *korbanot*? So I'm, yes. Ostensibly
makes the distinction between the משה *Moshe* broke and the one that
was actually in the... Oh, they're talking about the one of משה
*Moshe*? Yeah. Well why would that be relevant for somebody who's donating?
I don't know. It doesn't make any, it doesn't make
any
sense. The one of משה *Moshe*
broke was much,
much smaller. Yeah. I'm not getting it. I'm not getting it. All
right, let's keep on going. לבונה *levonah*, now we get to the
לבונה *levonah*. לא יפחות מקומץ *lo yifchos mikomitz*. It has to be
one hand-rest. נאמר כאן אזכרה *ne'emar kan azkarah*. It says by the
לבונה *levonah* אזכרה *azkarah*. It says, by the לחם Lechem הפנים *lechem
hapanim*, it says ונתת על המערכה לבונה זכה והיתה ללחם לאזכרה *v'nasata
al hama'arachah levonah zakah v'hayetah lalechem l'azkarah*. So it says אזכרה *azkarah*
by the לבונה *levonah* used by the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* because
that's what they would do by the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*. They
would burn the לבונה *levonah* that they had little sort of, you
know, spoons of לבונה *levonah* on the שולחן *shulchan*, one by each
מערכה *ma'arachah*, one by each column, and they'd burn the לבונה *levonah*
that would be sort of like the קומץ Kometz *kometz* of the
מנחה *minchah*, they'd burn that and then the כהנים *kohanim* would eat
the bread. They would do that once a week. So by the
לבונה *levonah* of לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, it says that it should
be as a remembrance, an אזכרה *azkarah*, ונאמר להלן אזכרה *v'ne'emar lehalan
azkarah*. And it says by the מנחה *minchah*, וקמץ משם מלא קמצו
מסלתה ומשמנה על כל לבונתה והקטיר הכהן את אזכרתה *v'kamatz misham milo
kumtzoh misaltah mishamnah al kol levonatah v'hiktir hakohen et azkaratah*. So it's
the same idea, right, the קומץ Kometz *kometz*, you take a hand-breadth
of the מנחה *minchah* and you put it on the altar and
you eat the rest of it. Also there's a, it's basically bread
is what the מנחה *minchah* is, and by the לבונה *levonah* you
take the by the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* you take the לבונה
*levonah* and you burn it and you eat the לחם *lechem*, and
they're both called an אזכרה *azkarah*. So based on that, we will
make a, we will make an analogy or we'll make a גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah*. מה אזכרה האמורה להלן מלא קמץ *mah azkarah ha'amurah
lehalan milo kometz*, the same way by a מנחה *minchah*, the whole
the אזכרה *azkarah* is the קומץ Kometz, *kometz*, is the hand-breadth of
the מנחה *minchah*, אף אזכרה האמורה כאן מלא קמץ *af azkarah ha'amurah
kan milo kometz*, even by the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, it is
מלא קמץ *milo kometz*, it is a hand-breadth. So basically it would
be a handful of קומץ Kometz *kometz* would be put in this
spoon by each column, and each column you'd offer up a, and
you'd offer up two of these, you know, the two spoons, once
a week. So that's the idea of a hand-breadth of a קומץ
Kometz *kometz* of קטורת *ketoret*, because each column would be one קומץ
Kometz *kometz* based on this connection to the קומץ Kometz? *kometz* of
the מנחה *minchah*. And they just sat and they ate bread, no
dips, no hummus? Yes. Maybe they could eat it together with the
קרבנות *korbanot*, they had a sandwich. Now whether כהנים *kohanim* could eat
certain types of things together with it, there is some, there's discussion
about that. Yes, whether allowed to put on certain types of a
condiment. Okay. Okay, now, גמרא *Gemara* תמהו *tamhu*: אם אזכרה האמורה להלן
שני קמצים ואין מנחה *im azkarah ha'amurah lehalan shene kematzim v'ein mincha*?
By the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, it's true it was one קומץ
Kometz *kometz* of לבונה *levonah* per column, but it was a total
of two. So why don't we say that the two is the
minimum? אימה אזכרה האמורה להלן שני קמצים אף אזכרה האמורה כאן שני
קמצים *ima azkarah ha'amurah lehalan shene kematzim af azkarah ha'amurah kan shene
kematzim*, why don't we say here too two is the minimum? אמר
רבי אילא כלום למדו קומץ Kometz אלא *amar Rabbi Ila, klum lamdu
kometz ella*, now as you can see there's a whole question once
again about גירסא *girsa*, אלא נלמד ממנחת חוטא *ella nelmad miminchas chotei*.
Now what's מנחת חוטא *minchas chotei* talking about? Why the emphasis of
מנחת חוטא *minchas chotei*? But anyway, אלא ממנחה *ella miminchah*. מה להלן
קומץ החסר פסול אף כאן קומץ החסר פסול *mah lehalan kometz hachaser
pasul af kan kometz hachaser pasul*. So what the heck does this
mean and why does it matter? So the same way by a
מנחת חוטא *minchas chotei*, if you have a lacking קומץ *kometz* it's
invalid, if your קומץ *kometz* for the for the מנחה *minchah*, so
here too by the לבונה *levonah* if it's if it's lacking and
not a full קומץ *kometz* it's invalid. Now first of all, how's
that relevant to the question? Of one of one קומץ versus two.
Number two is it's actually not so clear. There's some debate that
yes it's true that the קומץ of a מנחה if it's lacking
is invalid, but according to some the קומץ of the of the
לבונה by the לחם is not invalid. Anyway, the way so as
you can imagine there's a lot of discussion how to read this,
the way the קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah reads it is the following.
He says if it's invalid, he says but one minute, let's take
the following scenario. Let's say one of the two of the two
קומצים Komtzim by the two columns, one of them is missing a
little bit, is a little under קומץ, and one of them is
a little bit more. So is it- is the one- if we
say חסר is invalid, so we say the one that's missing is
invalid. Ah, he says, this proves that each one is independent, because
if you looked at the two as one unit, then anything that's
missing here you could always ask, well maybe there's extra here and
we look at it combined. So the fact that if it's missing
it's invalid and we don't look at the other קומץ shows that
each קומץ is independent and therefore that is a minimum קרבן, the
same way when each כהן Kohen brought individually one log of wood
even though combined it was two, we said one log is an
acceptable minimum. Here too one קומץ of קטורת is a minimum. Okay
let's do a little bit more. המתנדב לבונה HaMitnadev Levonah so okay
אמר רבי יוסי מילתיה דרבי אילא אמרה. Amar Rabbi Yosei milteih d'Rabbi
Ila amrah. So in the name of Rabbi Ila says המתנדב לבונה
HaMitnadev Levonah מביא כקומצו של כהן. meivi k'kumtzo shel kohen. Now there's
some that say כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, if you say whose
קומץ? Whose handbreadth? That's not an- that's not a fixed measure. So
he says you have to bring it in the handbreadth of the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Now why the heck the כהן גדול? Kohen
Gadol? So the actual interesting thing is is that according to the
way a number of מפרשים Mefarshim read this, it is the biggest
כהן. Kohen. Not the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the biggest כהן! Kohen!
So if you don't know which כהן Kohen is going to offer
it up and it has to be a handbreadth, so you have
to bring it based on the biggest כהן. Kohen. Okay? So רבי
חזקיה בשם רבי ירמיה ואפילו בקומץ בעלים. Rabbi Chizkiyah b'shem Rabbi Yirmiyah
v'afilu b'kometz baalim. No, you can bring it based on your handbreadth
and you can even bring it in the קומץ the קומץ of
yours and it does not have to be based on the כהן.
Kohen. Okay, we will- oh let's just read one more line here.
זהב לא יפחות Zahav lo yifchot if you say gold it's not
less than a דינר. אמר רבי אלעזר והוא שהזכיר צורה. Amar Rabbi
Elazar v'hu shehizkir tzurah. That's if you say I'm going to give
gold coins. Do you- you allude to coins. There you go Charlie,
your whole point of coins. אבל אם לא הזכיר צורה Aval im
lo hizkir tzurah if you just generically say gold, מביא אפילו צינורא
meivi afilu tzinora you can even bring like a- like a needle
of gold, a tiny amount or donate an appropriate tiny amount. Okay
we will pick up with the נדבה Nedava part tomorrow.